<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An invitation of love unto the seed of God throughout the world with a word to the wise in heart, and a lamentation for New-England : given forth from the movings of the spirit of the Lord / by ... Jone Brooksop.</title>
            <author>Brooksop, Jone, d. 1680.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1662</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 26 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A29718</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B4983</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R10126</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12713883</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12713883</idno>
            <idno type="VID">66148</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A29718)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 66148)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 680:25)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An invitation of love unto the seed of God throughout the world with a word to the wise in heart, and a lamentation for New-England : given forth from the movings of the spirit of the Lord / by ... Jone Brooksop.</title>
                  <author>Brooksop, Jone, d. 1680.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>15 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Robert Wilson,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1662]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Society of Friends --  New England.</term>
               <term>Devotional literature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:66148:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:66148:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN Invitation of LOVE UNTO THE SEED of GOD, Throughout the WORLD.</p>
            <p>With A WORD To the WISE in HEART. And A LAMENTATION For <hi>NEW-ENGLAND.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Given forth from the <hi>movings</hi> of the <hi>Spirit</hi> of the LORD, by one who is known to the World by the Name of <hi>JONE BROOKSOP.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Robert Wilſon.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:66148:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:66148:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>AN</hi> INVITATION of LOVE unto the <hi>Seed</hi> of <hi>GOD</hi> throughout the World, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>OH <hi>hearken</hi> all ye People of the Earth, and <hi>liſten</hi> all ye Inhabitants of the ſame: Oh <hi>hearken</hi> what the Lord <hi>ſpeakes</hi> to his People, He <hi>ſpeaks Peace</hi> unto his <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and to all them that put their <hi>truſt</hi> in him; for ſaith Chriſt Jeſus, <hi>I am the Light of the World, which doth enlighten every one that cometh into the World.</hi> Oh <hi>hearken</hi> to that of God <hi>in</hi> all your <hi>Conſciences,</hi> which <hi>checks</hi> for <hi>ſin</hi> and for <hi>iniquity,</hi> and for <hi>every thing</hi> that is <hi>contrary</hi> to that of God <hi>in</hi> all mens <hi>Conſciences,</hi> which is the <hi>Light</hi> which Chriſt Jeſus hath <hi>enlightened</hi> every one withal that cometh into the World. Oh my dear Friends, <hi>conſider</hi> the <hi>Loving kindneſs</hi> of the Lord God un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to your Souls, that he ſhould <hi>So love the World, as to ſend his onely begotten Son into the World, that they through him might believe; in whom is Life, and the Life is the Light of men.</hi> Oh let not the <hi>Loving Kindneſs</hi> of the Lord <hi>ſlip out of your Minds,</hi> but <hi>fear</hi> and <hi>dread</hi> before him, who made Heaven, and Earth, and all things that are there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in; and hath all Powers in his hand, and can turn them whenſoever it pleaſeth him, and howſoever it pleaſeth him. Oh <hi>fear</hi> and <hi>dread</hi> before his holy bleſſed Name for ever more, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:66148:3"/>
            <p>For at his Name muſt every knee <hi>bow,</hi> and every tongue <hi>confeſs,</hi> even at the Name of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> our Lord, and onely Saviour, and Redeemer, whom we witneſs come, <hi>to take away ſin in the fleſh;</hi> which all the Teachers in the World are ignorant of, that tell people, <hi>that they cannot be free from ſin while they live in this Life;</hi> which is contrary to Chriſt's Commands, which ſaith, <hi>Be ye perfect, as your heavenly Father is perfect:</hi> and, <hi>Be ye ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as I am holy:</hi> And ſo they keep poor people alwayes <hi>learning,</hi> and never able to come to the <hi>knowledge of the Truth, as it is in Jeſus.</hi> For Chriſt, <hi>he came not to call the Righteous, but Sinners to Repentance, that they through him might believe,</hi> in whom is <hi>Life</hi> and <hi>Salvation,</hi> for all them that believe in the <hi>Light</hi> which Chriſt Jeſus hath <hi>enlightened them withal.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſo all People, <hi>great</hi> and <hi>ſmall, high</hi> and <hi>low, rich</hi> and <hi>poor,</hi> of what ſort ſoever ye be, Mind the <hi>fear</hi> of the <hi>Lord God</hi> of <hi>Life,</hi> every one of you in your own per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars; while you <hi>have time,</hi> prize <hi>it;</hi> leſt the Lord come and <hi>ſmite the Earth with a Curſe:</hi> For aſſuredly, a <hi>Day</hi> of <hi>account</hi> muſt come upon <hi>all fleſh,</hi> to <hi>try all</hi> them that dwell upon the Earth, whether their <hi>deeds</hi> be wrought <hi>in God,</hi> yea or nay: For the Lord God of Life is <hi>riſen,</hi> and <hi>ariſing</hi> to <hi>plead</hi> with all the Inhabitants of the Earth, and they ſhall be as <hi>ſtubble</hi> before him; for our God is a <hi>terrible</hi> God unto the wicked, for all the <hi>proud,</hi> and all that <hi>do wickedly,</hi> ſhall be as <hi>ſtubble</hi> before <hi>Him</hi> with whom we have to do. For aſſuredly, a <hi>Day</hi> of <hi>Account</hi> muſt come upon all fleſh, to <hi>try</hi> them with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al; and every man's <hi>work</hi> that will no abide the <hi>fire,</hi> muſt be <hi>burnt up,</hi> of what <hi>ſort</hi> ſoever it ſhall be: For there is not a <hi>deed done</hi> in the <hi>Body,</hi> but an <hi>account</hi> muſt be
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:66148:3"/>given for it, whether it be <hi>good,</hi> or whether it be <hi>evil:</hi> the mouth of the Lord of Hoſts hath <hi>ſpoken it;</hi> Who will <hi>perform</hi> all his <hi>Promiſes</hi> made unto his own <hi>Seed.</hi> All <hi>praiſes</hi> be given unto him who <hi>made all things</hi> by the <hi>word</hi> of his <hi>Power,</hi> and <hi>Man</hi> to <hi>ſerve</hi> him. And now is his everlaſting <hi>Trumpet ſounding</hi> unto <hi>all Nations,</hi> that <hi>whoſoever will come and drink of the Rivers of Life freely,</hi> may come and <hi>buy Wine and Milk without Money and without price.</hi> And <hi>let every one that is a thirſt come, and whoſoever will, let him come, and take of the Water of Life freely:</hi> And ſo all People, who deſire to know Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for your own Souls, <hi>come</hi> to the <hi>Light</hi> which Chriſt Jeſus hath <hi>enlightened</hi> you withal. And <hi>now</hi> hath the Lord alone <hi>ſet up</hi> his <hi>Standard,</hi> and is <hi>diſplaying</hi> his <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign,</hi> that all Nations may <hi>come unto it</hi> and be <hi>ſaved,</hi> who is <hi>Iſrael</hi>'s <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Redeemer,</hi> from all <hi>Stormes,</hi> and <hi>Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſts,</hi> whatſoever may be ſuffered to come upon them to <hi>try</hi> them withal. Oh! my dearly beloved Friends, in whom there is <hi>any tenderneſs</hi> towards <hi>God</hi> and his <hi>Truth,</hi> conſider what you have been <hi>doing,</hi> and how you have <hi>ſpent</hi> your <hi>time,</hi> whether in the <hi>Service</hi> of the <hi>Lord,</hi> or in <hi>ſerving</hi> of your own <hi>Wills?</hi> To <hi>that in</hi> your <hi>Conſciences</hi> I ſpeak, which is <hi>God</hi>'s <hi>Witneſs,</hi> and will <hi>bear witneſs,</hi> againſt all that which is contrary to it in your own particulars.</p>
            <p>And if you love the <hi>Light,</hi> you will bring your deeds to the <hi>Light,</hi> that the <hi>Light</hi> may prove them, whether they be <hi>wrought in God</hi> yea or nay; but if you hate it, it will be your <hi>condemnation,</hi> (the Light) but I exhort thee whoever thou art, as thou tendereſt the good of thy own Soul, that thou <hi>love</hi> the <hi>Light</hi> which is the <hi>Life</hi> of <hi>Men,</hi> and <hi>embrace</hi> it, and <hi>love it</hi> with <hi>all thy heart,</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:66148:4"/>and with <hi>all thy mind,</hi> with <hi>all thy Soul,</hi> and with <hi>all thy ſtrength;</hi> Oh! <hi>love the Lord thy God with all thy heart, and thy Neighbour as thy ſelf;</hi> ſo ſhalt thou come to feel the <hi>Plant</hi> which the Lords right hand hath planted in thee, to grow up, if thou loveſt it; for this know aſuredly oh Man, that the Lord is come to look for Fruit, <hi>For he that ſows to the Fleſh, ſhall of the Fleſh reap Corruption; But he that ſowes to the Spirit, ſhall of the Spirit reap Life Everlaſting; and Joy and Peace, which ſhall never be taken from them;</hi> And ſo in tender love unto the Seed of God in all People, do I write, to warn all that love their own Souls, to fear and dread before the Lord God of Life and Power, for the Lord is at hand, as thouſands can witneſs at this day; all praiſes be given unto his holy Bleſſed Name for ever; for his <hi>Love</hi> is <hi>unſpeakable</hi> unto the Children of men, and his <hi>Ways paſt finding out;</hi> Oh! that men would praiſe the Lord for his goodneſs, and for his loving kindneſs towards the Children of men, <hi>for his Mercy endures for ever, throughout all Generations, unto ſuch as love his holy bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Name for ever:</hi> Oh, let the houſe of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> ſay, that his <hi>mercy endures for ever;</hi> and let the houſe of <hi>Jacob</hi> ſay, that his <hi>mercy endures for ever;</hi> and let the houſe of <hi>Aron</hi> ſay, that his <hi>Mercy endures for ever:</hi> Oh! let all them that know him ſay, that his <hi>Mercy endures for ever;</hi> and let all the Ranſomed ones of the Lord, ſay, that his <hi>Mercy endures for ever;</hi> who have taſted of his Everlaſting Love, which is ſhed abroad in our Hearts towards his own Seed: And in that Love which the Lord God of my Life hath loved me with all, do I exhort thee, and beſeech thee unto whom this may come, that thou ſlight not the day of thy Viſitation,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:66148:4"/>for if thou doſt, the Lord will ſlight thee, when the day of thy Calamity cometh upon thee to try thee; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I ſay unto thee, ſlight it not, leaſt the Lord come and ſpue thee out of his Mouth; and thou ſeek the Lord with tears as <hi>Eſau</hi> did, and could not find the Bleſſing; For the <hi>Spirit of the Lord ſhall not alwayes ſtrive with Man;</hi> therefore ſink down low to the witneſs of God in thee, that ſo thou mayeſt come to have Peace with God in thy own particular; and ſo being obedient unto the <hi>Light</hi> of Chriſt in thee, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by thou mayeſt come to witneſs victory over all that which hath vailed from thee the Pure Seed of God in thee; and ſo my dearly beloved Friend, unto whom my Life reaches, that all might come to the Knowledge of Life in themſelves, and live; which is the deſire of my Soul, and the deſire of all them that love and fear the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, who is my Life, and the length of my Dayes, in whom I live, not I, but Chriſt in me, the Hope of Glory, as the Scriptures of truth do bear witneſs: Unto that of God in all mens Conſciences do, I ſpeak, which is my witneſs and the Apoſtle bears wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the ſame when he ſaith, <hi>Know ye not, that Chriſt is in you except ye be reprobates;</hi> ſo then I ſay, as thou tende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt the good of thy immortal Soul, Dwell in the Light which is the way that leads to Life, which all the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, and all the Apoſtles, and all the Holy men of God did witneſs, <hi>Chriſt the Way, the Truth, and the Light,</hi> as thouſands can witneſs at this day; all <hi>Glory,</hi> and <hi>Hon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, Praiſe, Power,</hi> and <hi>Thanks</hi> be given unto his Bleſſed Holy Glorious Name for ever, and for ever; who firſt loved us, when we were in our Blood, he ſaid unto us, <hi>live,</hi> and is become unto us a place of
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:66148:5"/>broad Rivers, and Streams of Everlaſting Life, flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing into our Hearts, to nouriſh his own Plant in us, whom he hath called and choſen, to bear Teſtimony for his name Sake; everlaſting Pure Praiſes be given unto him, who liveth for ever, who is our <hi>King, Prieſt,</hi> and <hi>Law-Giver;</hi> unto whom the gathering is, and ſhall be for ever, all praiſes be given to his holy Name; for he is become unto us the <hi>chiefeſt among ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands, and more to be deſired than the Honey, or the Honey-Combe, of all them that fear him and keep his Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments;</hi> and more to be <hi>Embraced</hi> then <hi>fine Gold:</hi> And as we abide faithful unto the Lord, we know that we ſhall all ſit down with <hi>Abraham, Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi> where none ſhall make us afraid, though <hi>ten thouſands</hi> riſe up againſt us, yet ſhall we not <hi>fear what man can do unto us;</hi> for our God is on our ſide, <hi>Who then can be againſt us?</hi> who works all our <hi>Works in us and for us</hi> continually; who never ceaſes to adminiſter daily refreſhment unto his own Seed in us; Everlaſting ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Praiſes be given unto my Heavenly Father, who is my <hi>Eternal Portion,</hi> and my <hi>exceeding great reward;</hi> who hath <hi>redeemed me from Death to Life, and from under the Power of Satan unto God,</hi> and hath ſet my feet upon a Rock, which <hi>Rock</hi> is <hi>Chriſt in me, the hope of Glory;</hi> In <hi>whom I live, and move, and have my Being;</hi> and unto him alone belongeth all the Glory; for of my ſelf I can do nothing: But it is he that worketh all his Works in me by the <hi>Word</hi> of his own <hi>Power;</hi> by which I ſtand even at this preſent time, and am pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved through all Straits by Sea and by Land, and through <hi>good report</hi> and <hi>evil report,</hi> and whatſoever may come for his Name Sake; <hi>Who ſo loved the World,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:66148:5"/>that he ſent his only begotten Son into the World, that who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever believes in him ſhould not periſh, but ſhould have Everlaſting Life abiding in them;</hi> for he came to ſave <hi>Sinners,</hi> of whom I was the <hi>chief;</hi> but now I am <hi>waſhed</hi> and <hi>cleanſed</hi> through the <hi>Blood of Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> which God hath revealed in me by the Revelation of his on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly begotten Son, without which none can ſee God, and live.</p>
            <p>This is to go all over the Earth, that ſo People may come to ſee their Sins, and repent, and live; gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven forth from the moving of the Spirit of the Lord God, in tender Love unto the Seed of God in all mens Conſciences to whom I write, who am a true lover of <hi>Iſraels Good,</hi> and would have none to periſh in their Sins, but that all might come to the Knowledge of him, and live, in whom is <hi>Life</hi> and <hi>Salvation,</hi> and with him there is <hi>Plenteous Redemption</hi> for evermore, that he may be feared and worſhipped in Spirit and in Truth, for ſuch is the Father ſeeking to worſhip him, as do worſhip him in Spirit and in Truth; as thouſands do witneſs in theſe our dayes, in whom he hath revealed the Image of his only begotten Son in our hearts, Jeſus Chriſt our Lord, and only Saviour, in <hi>whom we live, and move, and have our Being,</hi> who is the <hi>Rock</hi> of <hi>Ages,</hi> and <hi>Generations;</hi> ſo that Generations which are to come, ſhall bleſs and praiſe his holy Name for theſe our dayes, wherein he hath made known of the Riches of his Grace, and of his Majeſty in our Hearts, and hath ſhed it abroad unto all <hi>Nations, Kindreds,</hi> and <hi>People,</hi> that ſo they might come to the knowledge of Salvation for their Immortal Souls, and live in whom is Life.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:66148:6"/>
            <p>O all People be obedient unto that of God in your own Conſciences, which makes manifeſt the deeds of darkneſs in your own particulars, that you may come to feel the ſprings of Life to nouriſh the Plant, which his own right hand hath planted in you. O love the <hi>Light</hi> that leads to <hi>Life</hi> and <hi>Salvation;</hi> O let it take im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion in your hearts, ſo ſhall it be worn in the inward part of the mind, which is the ſearcher of all ſecrets, and knows the intents of the ſame; for they are all na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked and bare before him. O my dearly beloved Friend, in whoſe hearts there is any tender deſires be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten, Keep to the <hi>Light,</hi> and dwell low in it; for if ever thou come'ſt to know Salvation for thy Soul, thou muſt know it in thee; for Chriſt ſaith, that <hi>none cometh unto the Father, but by me,</hi> and <hi>none knoweth the Father but the Son, and he to whom the Son revealeth him;</hi> and he ſaith, <hi>I and my Father are one;</hi> and he ſaith, <hi>Ye are my Friends if ye do whatſoever I command you to do;</hi> and his <hi>Commandements are not grievous but joyous unto all them that keep them in truth and uprightneſs of heart and mind;</hi> unto whom the <hi>Son of Righteouſneſs is riſen, with heal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in his wings; and he will thorowly purge his floor, and will gather his wheat into his garner, but the chaffe will he burn with unquenchable fire.</hi> O fear and dread before him, for he is a God of Love to his own Seed, but a ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible God unto the wicked, and all the ungodly ſhall be as ſtubble before him; and there ſhall be <hi>weeping,</hi> and <hi>wailing,</hi> and <hi>gnaſhing</hi> of <hi>teeth;</hi> and there ſhall be none to help them. Therefore return with ſpeed, while ye have time prize it, leſt it be hid from your eyes, and ye <hi>periſh</hi> in your <hi>ſins,</hi> and there be none to help you; for there is no <hi>redemption</hi> in the <hi>Grave,</hi> as the <hi>Tree falls</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:66148:6"/>ſo it <hi>lyes,</hi> and as <hi>death leaves it,</hi> ſo <hi>Judgement ſhall find it;</hi> and the <hi>ungodly</hi> ſhall <hi>periſh</hi> in their <hi>ungodlineſs,</hi> but the <hi>righteous</hi> ſhall <hi>flouriſh like a green Bay-Tree;</hi> and they ſhall <hi>reign</hi> over their <hi>enemies</hi> within and without, for the <hi>Lamb</hi> ſhal have the <hi>Victory</hi> over all his enemies that may ariſe to oppoſe him; for his <hi>Dominion is an everlaſting Dominion, and of his Government there ſhall be no end; who rules all Nations with a rod of iron, before whom all the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the Earth are but as the drop of a bucket;</hi> for <hi>he will daſh them in pieces as a potters veſſel, yea they ſhall call to the Mountains to cover them, and the Hills to fall upon them</hi> in that day when the Lord ſhall call them to an account for all their life time; O that thou wouldeſt lay this to heart, whoſoever thou art that art in this Condition, and fear and dread before the living God of Life and Salvation, whoſe preſence is dreadful unto the wicked.</p>
            <p>O my dearly beloved Friends and fellow Citizens of the <hi>houſhold of God,</hi> who are <hi>come</hi> to the <hi>Heavenly Jeruſalem,</hi> the <hi>City</hi> of the <hi>Saints ſolemnity,</hi> where all the <hi>faithful ones</hi> ſhall <hi>lye down together,</hi> and <hi>drink</hi> of the <hi>Rivers</hi> of <hi>Life,</hi> which run <hi>freely:</hi> Oh <hi>drink, drink my beloved friends</hi> of the <hi>virtue</hi> of the <hi>ſtreams</hi> of my <hi>heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Father's Love,</hi> which run <hi>freely</hi> and <hi>plenteouſly,</hi> for all them that do <hi>wait</hi> upon him in his holy bleſſed <hi>fear</hi> for ever, and hath <hi>him alone</hi> to be their <hi>hiding-place,</hi> of whoſe <hi>fulneſs</hi> there is <hi>no end;</hi> for he gives <hi>freely</hi> and <hi>upbraids none.</hi> Oh my dearly beloved Friends, unto whom my Life reacheth, Read me in the Covenant of <hi>Light,</hi> and <hi>Life,</hi> and <hi>Peace,</hi> where our <hi>Unity</hi> ſtands, in that which was before words were, and ſhall be when words ſhal be no more, even in <hi>that</hi> by which the <hi>World</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:66148:7"/>was <hi>made,</hi> and all things were <hi>created,</hi> and are <hi>upheld</hi> to this day, even by the <hi>word</hi> of his <hi>Power:</hi> And ſo all dear Friends, <hi>hold faſt your Confidence without wrath or doubting unto the end,</hi> and in the <hi>end,</hi> that ſo ye may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive a <hi>Crown of Life,</hi> which is laid up for all them that endure faithful unto the end; for aſſuredly, <hi>ye ſhall all reap if ye faint not;</hi> but ſtand faſt, and keep your inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grity, oh dwell low in the feeling of the pure power of the Lord God of Life continually, that with it you may come to fathom over all the World, both within and without, and live unto God who is the Father of Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, that ſo ye may come unto the <hi>New Jeruſalem,</hi> the <hi>City of the living God, and unto the ſpirits of juſt men made perfect by the blood of the Lamb, which was ſlain from the foundation of the World;</hi> but now hath the Lord made him known in theſe our dayes; everlaſting holy <hi>praiſes</hi> be given unto his glorious Name for evermore, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Oh the <hi>riches</hi> of his <hi>Grace</hi> and <hi>Love,</hi> which he hath ſhed abroad in our hearts, towards his own <hi>Seed,</hi> who hath taken upon him the Government, and of whoſe Dominion there ſhall be no end, for he is come to Rule <hi>whoſe Right it is;</hi> everlaſting, glorious, powerful, holy <hi>praiſes</hi> be given unto him for ever, my Father of <hi>Life</hi> in whom I live for ever; who is my ſtrength, and the length of my days, and my portion for ever, and my exceeding great reward, who have forſaken all my Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, Husband, &amp; Children, and whatſoever was near and dear unto me, yea &amp; my own Life too, for his own Names ſake: Everlaſting <hi>praiſes</hi> be given unto his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Name for ever, who hath counted me worthy to bear a <hi>Teſtimony</hi> for his Names ſake, and hath fulfilled that Scripture, which he ſpake to his Diſciples, when
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:66148:7"/>he ſaid, <hi>He that will not forſake Father and Mother, Wife and Children, for my Names ſake and the Goſpels, is not worthy of me;</hi> yea, <hi>and his own Life too:</hi> Which I do witneſs in my meaſure, <hi>Hallelujahs</hi> be given to the Higheſt for ever, who am a true lover of the <hi>Seed</hi> of God, and it is the deſire of my heart, that all may come to the knowledge of him in their own particulars, and live to God, in whom is <hi>Life</hi> and plenteous <hi>Redem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption</hi> for evermore, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>J. B.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <head>A LAMENTATION for <hi>New-England.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>OH <hi>New-England repent,</hi> I ſay unto thee <hi>repent,</hi> for in thee is found the <hi>Blood</hi> of the Saints, and the <hi>Cry</hi> of <hi>it</hi> is entered into the ears of the Lord of Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baths, and <hi>it</hi> is come before him, for he is riſen to <hi>plead</hi> with all fleſh by the <hi>ſword</hi> of his <hi>mouth,</hi> and the <hi>bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> of his <hi>coming,</hi> and he will <hi>terribly ſhake</hi> the <hi>Earth,</hi> and it ſhall be as <hi>ſtubble</hi> before him; for he is riſen to make <hi>inquiſition for blood:</hi> Oh how will you <hi>ſtand</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him? or, what will you <hi>anſwer</hi> him when he ſhall call you to an <hi>account,</hi> for all your ungodly deeds, that ye have ungodlily committed againſt the Lord and his Truth? or, what will you <hi>anſwer</hi> when he ſhall make <hi>inquiſition for blood?</hi> Oh howl and weep ye Rulers of <hi>Boſton,</hi> for the men of <hi>Nineveh</hi> ſhall riſe up in Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment againſt you, <hi>for they repented at the Preaching of</hi> Jonas, <hi>but a greater than</hi> Jonas <hi>is here;</hi> but you have hardned your hearts againſt his ſervants, and againſt
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:66148:8"/>the witneſs of God in your Conſciences. Oh how is your beauty ſtained ſince the day the Lord firſt viſited you? and, how is your Light become Dark, yea even groſs Darkneſs that may be felt, and blind as ever the <hi>Sodomites</hi> were? Oh how doth my Soul pity you, that ever ye ſhould be ſo ignorant of your own Salvation, to turn the truth of our God into a ly, and put his Servants to death, when he ſent them among you to warn you of the Wrath to come, which is coming upon all the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants of the Earth, except they <hi>repent;</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hath he ſent his Servants and Hand-maids amongſt you to warn you in tender love to your immortal Souls, but how have ye rewarded the Lord evil for good? and he looked that ye ſhould have brought forth good fruit, but behold briars and thorns, and ye have made your ſelves a ſtink to all Nations round about you. Oh come down to the witneſs of God in your Conſciences which will let you ſee what you have done, and if you love it, it will bring you to repentance, even the <hi>Light</hi> which Chriſt Jeſus hath enlightened every one withal, that cometh into the World; and if ye hate it, it will be your condemnation, even the <hi>Light;</hi> unto that in your Conſciences I ſpeak, which is God's Witneſs, and my Witneſs, which never conſented to ſin, but ever ſtands a Witneſs againſt it, in all your Conſciences, and is even preſſed as a Cart is preſſed with ſheaves. Oh that every one of you were made ſenſible of it, then would you not ſo kick againſt it as you do at this day, even as the <hi>Gadarens</hi> did at Chriſt, who beſought him <hi>to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part out of their coaſts;</hi> even ſo have ye made <hi>Lawes,</hi> and <hi>Gallows,</hi> and <hi>Priſons,</hi> and <hi>Whips,</hi> what not, that can be invented againſt the people of God. Oh how are you
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:66148:8"/>found fighting againſt the Lord and his Witneſs in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one of your Conſciences: for aſſuredly a <hi>Day</hi> of <hi>Account</hi> ye muſt give unto the Lord God of Life, who hath all Powers in his hands, and can turn them when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever it pleaſeth him, and howſoever it pleaſeth him. Oh what will you anſwer him when he ſhall call you to an account? Oh ye Rulers of <hi>Boſton,</hi> my heart is made ſad when I remember your condition and your ſtate, how you are found out of the ways of God, againſt your own Soules. Oh <hi>New-England,</hi> how is your <hi>beauty</hi> become <hi>aſhes,</hi> and your <hi>glory</hi> turned into <hi>ſhame?</hi> and how have ye <hi>forgotten the Lord your Maker, and the Rock from whence ye were hewn, and are found fighting againſt him?</hi> But this know all ye that <hi>forget God,</hi> and <hi>kick at his reproof,</hi> and will <hi>have none of his Counſel,</hi> but <hi>ſlight his Meſſengers,</hi> and the <hi>Witneſs</hi> of <hi>God</hi> in your own <hi>Conſciences;</hi> yea know this aſſuredly, that ye can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not <hi>hide</hi> your ſelves from <hi>the Wrath of the Lamb,</hi> and his <hi>preſence;</hi> For, <hi>Who art thou, oh man, that art found ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving againſt thy Maker? Have not I all Power in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and in Earth, to do with them as ſeemeth good in my ſight? ſaith the Lord God Almighty.</hi> Oh that man could <hi>praiſe the Lord for his Mercies</hi> and <hi>his Goodneſs towards the Sons of Men!</hi> And ſay not but that you were <hi>warn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi> in your Life time, by one who is a true <hi>lover</hi> of the <hi>Seed</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> known unto the World by the Name of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Jone Brooksop.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <date>The 4th Month, 1662.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
